Now if you're watching us in Europe, you may well be enjoying a very strong coffee.
It's early morning and a good cup of coffee is required.
But is our traditional picker-upper in danger of becoming a luxury as prices soar?
Well like other foods, the cost of coffee has gone through the roof.
On international markets, the price of coffee, especially Arabica, has seen dramatic increases,
in some cases going up by 70% over the past year.
Jason Archie Achienpong from the Fairtrade Foundation told me why farmers are unable to keep up with demand.
It's a supply and demand issue, right?
But fundamentally with farmers, farmers are just unable to supply the beans that we so greatly need, right?
For years of underpayment, they've been unable to invest in their farms.
And then you couple that with the fact you now have climate change, which is causing real devastation across many farms.
You've now got a recipe for disaster.
And so the demand has remained high.
Consumers were still drinking our coffee,
but farmers themselves are just unable to supply the beans
because of the issues that they face right now on the ground.
So consequently, the price of coffee is going up and up.
And America I assuming are huge consumers And for them they seeing even higher prices because of tariffs Rightly so rightly so I think there are a range of factors as well
sort of geopolitical tensions,
which are causing challenges across shipping routes
in terms of supplying coffee out of regions such as East Africa.
But then also, when we look at factors such as the tariffs,
as you mentioned, right,
Brazil is arguably one of the leading exporters of Arabica coffee,
also Robusta as well.
And, you know, the recent imposition of tariffs on the nation has caused real volatility and also uncertainty in the market.
And that creates real significant challenges as well on the pricing of coffee as well.
And with prices rising significantly, and you just explained why that is, does that mean the choice to go sustainable is less likely?
In fact, you know, the choice to go sustainable is even more so important.
As we see, when we look at pricing at the moment and the challenges we're facing, the
issue is mainly because farmers have not been invested and they have been unable to invest
in their farms and are now tackling real key issues on the ground.
Recent studies have shown that by 2050, nearly 50% of the global surface area currently used
for coffee farming may no longer be suitable.